Other people. Everyone is interested in other people.
الآخرون. كل شخص مهتم بالآخرين.
Everyone has relationships with other people,
الجميع لهم علاقات تربطهم بالآخرين،
and they're interested in these relationships
وهم مهتمون بتلك العلاقات
for a variety of reasons.
لأسباب عديدة
Good relationships, bad relationships,
علاقات جيدة، علاقات سيئة،
annoying relationships, agnostic relationships,
علاقات مزعجة، علاقات مضطربة،
and what I'm going to do is focus on the central piece
وما سأفعله هو التركيز على الجزء الأساسي
of an interaction that goes on in a relationship.
للتفاعل الذي يجري في علاقةٍ ما.
So I'm going to take as inspiration the fact that we're all
سأتخذ من حقيقة كوننا جميعا مهتمّون
interested in interacting with other people,
بالتفاعل مع الغير كمصدر إلهام.
I'm going to completely strip it of all its complicating features,
سأجرده من كل خصائصه المعقدة،
and I'm going to turn that object, that simplified object,
وسأقوم بتحويل ذلك الشيء، ذلك الشيء البسيط
into a scientific probe, and provide the early stages,
إلى تحقيق علميّ، وسأقوم بالكشف عن المراحل الأولى،
embryonic stages of new insights into what happens
المراحل الجنينيّة لرؤى جديدة عن حقيقة ما يحدث
in two brains while they simultaneously interact.
داخل دماغين أثناء تفاعلهما معاً.
But before I do that, let me tell you a couple of things
لكن قبل أن أقوم بذلك، دعني أخبركم عن بعض الأمور
that made this possible.
التي جعلت ذلك ممكناً.
The first is we can now eavesdrop safely
الأمر الأول هو أننا نستطيع الآن أن نتجسس
on healthy brain activity.
بأمان على نشاط دماغ سليم.
Without needles and radioactivity,
من دون استخدام الإبر أو النشاط الإشعاعي،
without any kind of clinical reason, we can go down the street
من دون أي نوع من الاستنتاجات السريرية، يمكننا النزول إلى الشارع
and record from your friends' and neighbors' brains
والتدوين من أدمغة أصدقائك أو جيرانك
while they do a variety of cognitive tasks, and we use
أثناء قيامهم بالعديد من المهمات الإدراكية، ونحن نستخدم
a method called functional magnetic resonance imaging.
طريقة تسمى بالتصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي الوظيفي.
You've probably all read about it or heard about in some
ولابد أنكم جميعاً قد قرأتهم أو سمعتم عنه في بعض
incarnation. Let me give you a two-sentence version of it.
العناوين. دعوني أفسّره لكم في جملتين.
So we've all heard of MRIs. MRIs use magnetic fields
سمعنا جميعاً بالتصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي. يُستخدم فيه مجال مغناطيسي
and radio waves and they take snapshots of your brain
وموجات إشعاعية تقوم بالتقاط صورة لدماغك
or your knee or your stomach,
أو ركبتك أو معدتك،
grayscale images that are frozen in time.
صور لا لونيّة يتم تجميدها في الوقت المناسب.
In the 1990s, it was discovered you could use
في التسعينات، اكتُشف أن بإمكانك استخدام
the same machines in a different mode,
نفس الآلات بطريقة مختلفة،
and in that mode, you could make microscopic blood flow
ويمكنك بتلك الطريقة صنع أفلام مجهرية لتدفق
movies from hundreds of thousands of sites independently in the brain.
الدم من مئات آلاف المواقع في الدماغ بشكل مستقل.
Okay, so what? In fact, the so what is, in the brain,
حسناً، وماذا في ذلك؟ في الواقع، في الدماغ،
changes in neural activity, the things that make your brain work,
التغييرات في النشاط العصبي، الأشياء التي تجعل دماغك يعمل،
the things that make your software work in your brain,
الأشياء التي تجعل البرمجة تعمل بدماغك،
are tightly correlated with changes in blood flow.
هي مرتبطة بشدة بالتغييرات في تدفق الدم.
You make a blood flow movie, you have an independent
فعندما تصنع فيلما لتدفق الدم، يكون لديك وكيل
proxy of brain activity.
وكيل لنشاط الدماغ.
This has literally revolutionized cognitive science.
وقد أحدث ذلك، بشكل حرفي، ثورة في العلوم المعرفية.
Take any cognitive domain you want, memory,
خذ أي مجال معرفي تريد، الذاكرة
motor planning, thinking about your mother-in-law,
التخطيط الحركي، التفكير في حماتك،
getting angry at people, emotional response, it goes on and on,
غضبك من الآخرين، الاستجابة العاطفية والقائمة تطول.
put people into functional MRI devices, and
ضع الناس في أجهزة التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي،
image how these kinds of variables map onto brain activity.
و قم بتصوير كيفيّة ارتباط هذه الأنواع من المتغيرات بنشاط الدماغ.
It's in its early stages, and it's crude by some measures,
إنّها في مراحلها المبكرة، وهي أولية ببعض المقاييس،
but in fact, 20 years ago, we were at nothing.
لكن في الحقيقة، منذ عشرين عاماً، لم نتوصّل إلى شيء.
You couldn't do people like this. You couldn't do healthy people.
لم نكن نستطيع القيام بذلك على الأشخاص، على الأشخاص الأصحّاء.
That's caused a literal revolution, and it's opened us up
وهذا ما تسبّب بالثورة، وقد أوصلتنا
to a new experimental preparation. Neurobiologists,
إلى إعداد تجريبي جديد. علماء بيولوجيا الأعصاب،
as you well know, have lots of experimental preps,
كما تعرفونهم جيداً، لديهم الكثير من التحضيرات التجريبية،
worms and rodents and fruit flies and things like this.
ديدان وقوارض وذباب الفاكهة و ما شابه.
And now, we have a new experimental prep: human beings.
والآن، لدينا محضر تجريبي جديد: البشر.
We can now use human beings to study and model
يمكننا الآن استخدام البشر لدراسة وصياغة
the software in human beings, and we have a few
البرمجة في البشر، ولدينا القليل من
burgeoning biological measures.
الاستعدادات البيولوجية النّاشئة.
Okay, let me give you one example of the kinds of experiments that people do,
حسناً، دعوني أعطيكم مثالا لأنواع التجارب التي يجريها الناس،
and it's in the area of what you'd call valuation.
وهو في مجال ما نسمّيه بالتّقييم.
Valuation is just what you think it is, you know?
التقييم هو، كما تعلمون
If you went and you were valuing two companies against
عندما تذهب وتقيّم شركة مقابل شركة
one another, you'd want to know which was more valuable.
أخرى، فأنت تريد أن تعرف أيهما أكثر قيمة.
Cultures discovered the key feature of valuation thousands of years ago.
اكتشفت الثقافات السمة الرئيسية للتقييم منذ آلاف السنين.
If you want to compare oranges to windshields, what do you do?
إذا أردت أن تقارن بين البرتقال والزجاج الأمامي، فماذا تفعل؟
Well, you can't compare oranges to windshields.
حسناً، لا يمكنك أن تقارن البرتقال بالزجاج الأمامي.
They're immiscible. They don't mix with one another.
لا يمكن المزج بينهما. كلاهما لا يختلط مع الآخر.
So instead, you convert them to a common currency scale,
فبدلاً عن ذلك، تحوّلها إلى مقياس شائع،
put them on that scale, and value them accordingly.
تضعهما على ذلك المقياس وتقيّمهما وفقاً لذلك.
Well, your brain has to do something just like that as well,
يقوم دماغك بفعل نفس الشيء كذلك،
and we're now beginning to understand and identify
وبدأنا الآن في فهم وتحديد
brain systems involved in valuation,
أنظمة الدماغ المشاركة في التقييم.
and one of them includes a neurotransmitter system
وواحد منها يتّضمن نظام الناقل العصبي
whose cells are located in your brainstem
التي تقع خلاياه في جذع المخ
and deliver the chemical dopamine to the rest of your brain.
وتنقل مادة الدوبامين الكيميائية إلى باقي الدماغ.
I won't go through the details of it, but that's an important
لن أخوض في التفاصيل، لكنها اكتشاف
discovery, and we know a good bit about that now,
مهم، ونحن نعرف القليل عنه،
and it's just a small piece of it, but it's important because
وهو جزء بسيط من النظام، لكنه مهم لأنه
those are the neurons that you would lose if you had Parkinson's disease,
يمثّل تلك الخلايا العصبية التي تفقدها إذا أُصبت بمرض باركنسون،
and they're also the neurons that are hijacked by literally
وهي أيضاً الخلايا العصبية التي تم اختطافها بأتمّ معنى الكلمة
every drug of abuse, and that makes sense.
من قبل أيّ عقار مؤدّ للإدمان، وهذا منطقي.
Drugs of abuse would come in, and they would change
العقار المؤدي للإدمان سيدخل، وسيغيّر
the way you value the world. They change the way
الطريقة التي تقيّم بها العالم. ويغيّر الطريقة
you value the symbols associated with your drug of choice,
التي تقيّم بها الرموز المرتبطة بعقارك المفضل،
and they make you value that over everything else.
ويجعلك تقدّرها أكثر من أي شيء آخر.
Here's the key feature though. These neurons are also
وإليك السمة الأساسية. هذه الخلايا العصبية تشترك
involved in the way you can assign value to literally abstract ideas,
كذلك في طريقة تعيينك لقيمة الأفكار المجردة،
and I put some symbols up here that we assign value to
وقد وضعت بعض الرموز هنا التي نعيّن قيمة لها
for various reasons.
لأسباب متنوعة.
We have a behavioral superpower in our brain,
لدينا قوة خارقة سلوكية في دماغنا،
and it at least in part involves dopamine.
وهي تحتوي جزئياً على مادة الدوبامين.
We can deny every instinct we have for survival for an idea,
يمكننا أن ننكر كل غريزة لدينا للبقاء على قيد الحياة لأجل فكرة،
for a mere idea. No other species can do that.
فقط مجرد فكرة. الأنواع الأخرى لا يمكنها القيام بذلك.
In 1997, the cult Heaven's Gate committed mass suicide
في عام 1997، طائفة Heaven's Gate أقدمت على الانتحار الجماعي
predicated on the idea that there was a spaceship
مبنيّا على فكرة أن هناك سفينة فضائية
hiding in the tail of the then-visible comet Hale-Bopp
تختبئ في ذيل المذنب Hale-Bopp الذي كان مرئيّا آنذاك
waiting to take them to the next level. It was an incredibly tragic event.
منتظرين أن يتمّ نقلهم إلى المستوى التّالي. وهو حدث مأساوي بشكل لا يصدق.
More than two thirds of them had college degrees.
وكان لأكثر من ثلثيهم شهادات جامعية.
But the point here is they were able to deny their instincts for survival
ولكن العبرة هنا أنّهم كانوا قادرين على إنكار غرائزهم للبقاء على قيد الحياة
using exactly the same systems that were put there
باستخدام نفس الأنظمة التي كانت موجودة
to make them survive. That's a lot of control, okay?
لجعلهم يبقون على قيد الحياة. يتطلّب الأمر الكثير من التحكم.
One thing that I've left out of this narrative
هناك شيء واحد لم أذكره الأن،
is the obvious thing, which is the focus of the rest of my
هو الشيء الواضح، الذي هو محور بقية محادثتي
little talk, and that is other people.
وهو الناس الآخرون.
These same valuation systems are redeployed
يعاد توزيع نفس أنظمة التقييم هذه
when we're valuing interactions with other people.
عندما نقوم بتقييم التفاعلات مع أشخاص آخرين.
So this same dopamine system that gets addicted to drugs,
لذا نظام الدوبامين هذا نفسه الذي يصبح مدمنا على المخدرات
that makes you freeze when you get Parkinson's disease,
و الذي يصيبك بالشلل عند إصابتك بمرض باركنسون،
that contributes to various forms of psychosis,
الذي له دور في ظهور مختلف أشكال الذهان،
is also redeployed to value interactions with other people
له أيضا دور في التفاعل مع النّاس
and to assign value to gestures that you do
وتعيين قيمة للإيماءات التي يمكنك القيام بها
when you're interacting with somebody else.
عندما تتفاعل مع شخص آخر.
Let me give you an example of this.
واسمحوا لي أن أقدم لكم مثالاً على ذلك.
You bring to the table such enormous processing power
نضيف إلى الجدول قوة معالجة هائلة
in this domain that you hardly even notice it.
في هذا المجال لا نكاد حتى نحسّ بها.
Let me just give you a few examples. So here's a baby.
اسمحوا لي أن أقدم لكم بعض الأمثلة. هذا طفل رضيع.
She's three months old. She still poops in her diapers and she can't do calculus.
عمرها ثلاثة أشهر. لا تزال تتغوط في حفاضات الأطفال و بالطبع لا تستطيع القيام بالعمليات الحسابية.
She's related to me. Somebody will be very glad that she's up here on the screen.
هي من أقربائي. سيسعد شخصا ما كثيرا لرؤية صورتها هنا على الشاشة.
You can cover up one of her eyes, and you can still read
يمكنك تغطية أحد عينيها، ويمكنك أن ترى
something in the other eye, and I see sort of curiosity
شيئا ما في العين الأخرى، أنا أرى نوعا من الفضول
in one eye, I see maybe a little bit of surprise in the other.
في عين، و أرى ربما قليلا من التفاجؤ في الأخرى.
Here's a couple. They're sharing a moment together,
هنا فردان يتقاسمان لحظة حميمة معا،
and we've even done an experiment where you can cut out
وأجرينا حتّى تجربة حيث يمكنك قص
different pieces of this frame and you can still see
قطع مختلفة من هذا الإطار، ويمكنك أن ترى أنّهما
that they're sharing it. They're sharing it sort of in parallel.
لا يزالان يتقاسمان تلك المشاعر بشكل متواز نوعا ما.
Now, the elements of the scene also communicate this
الآن، عناصر المشهد أيضا تكشف لنا
to us, but you can read it straight off their faces,
هذا، لكن يمكننا أيضا أن نرى هذا في وجوههما،
and if you compare their faces to normal faces, it would be a very subtle cue.
وإذا قارنت وجوههما بالوجوه العادية، ستلاحظ الاختلاف بدقة.
Here's another couple. He's projecting out at us,
هذا زوج آخر، هو يكشف لنا
and she's clearly projecting, you know,
و هي أيضا تكشف لنا
love and admiration at him.
مشاعر الحب والاعجاب تجاهه.
Here's another couple. (Laughter)
هنا زوج آخر. (ضحك)
And I'm thinking I'm not seeing love and admiration on the left. (Laughter)
و أنا أفكّر في أنّنا لا نرى الحب والاعجاب على اليسار. (ضحك)
In fact, I know this is his sister, and you can just see
في الواقع، تلك هي شقيقته، ويمكنك أن تراه
him saying, "Okay, we're doing this for the camera,
يقول "حسنا، نحن نفعل هذا لأجل الكاميرا،
and then afterwards you steal my candy and you punch me in the face." (Laughter)
وثم بعد ذلك ستعودين لسرقة الحلوى خاصّتي و لكمي في الوجه. " (ضحك)
He'll kill me for showing that.
سيقتلني بسبب عرض هذه الصورة.
All right, so what does this mean?
إذن، ما الذي يعنيه كلّ هذا؟
It means we bring an enormous amount of processing power to the problem.
هذا يعني أنّنا نحمل كمية هائلة من طاقة المعالجة لهذه المشكلة.
It engages deep systems in our brain, in dopaminergic
وهو يشرك الأنظمة العميقة في الدماغ، في الأنطمة الدوباميطاقية
systems that are there to make you chase sex, food and salt.
المسؤولة عن غرائز البحث عن الجنس أو الطعام و الملح.
They keep you alive. It gives them the pie, it gives
هي تبقينا على قيد الحياة. تعطينا الفطيرة، تعطينا
that kind of a behavioral punch which we've called a superpower.
نوعا من اللّكمة السلوكيّة و التي سمّيناها بالقوة الخارقة.
So how can we take that and arrange a kind of staged
فكيف يمكننا أن نستفيد من ذلك و نخلق نوعا من
social interaction and turn that into a scientific probe?
التفاعل الاجتماعي وتحويله إلى تحقيق علمي؟
And the short answer is games.
الإجابة القصيرة هي: الألعاب.
Economic games. So what we do is we go into two areas.
الألعاب الاقتصادية. ما نقوم به هو أنّنا الخوض في مجالين.
One area is called experimental economics. The other area is called behavioral economics.
الأول هو الاقتصاد التجريبي والثاني هو الاقتصاد السلوكي.
And we steal their games. And we contrive them to our own purposes.
نقوم بسرقة ألعابهم و نستخدمها في أغراضنا الخاصة.
So this shows you one particular game called an ultimatum game.
هذا يظهر لكم لعبة تسمى لعبة إنذار.
Red person is given a hundred dollars and can offer
يتمّ إعطاء الشخص الأحمر 100 دولار، ويمكنه أن يعرض
a split to blue. Let's say red wants to keep 70,
أن يقسم مع الشخص الأزرق. دعونا نفترض أنّ الأحمر يريد إبقاء 70،
and offers blue 30. So he offers a 70-30 split with blue.
و يعطي الأزرق 30. حيث أنه يتقاسم 70-30 مع الأزرق.
Control passes to blue, and blue says, "I accept it,"
فينال الأزرق التّحكم و يقبل بالمبلغ،
in which case he'd get the money, or blue says,
في هذه الحالة سيحصل على المال، أو يمكنه أن يرفض
"I reject it," in which case no one gets anything. Okay?
و في هذه الحالة لا يحصل أيّ منهما على أيّ شيء.
So a rational choice economist would say, well,
عالم اقتصاد ذو قرار عقلانيّ قد يقول
you should take all non-zero offers.
عليك أن تقبل بكلّ عرض تنال فيه مالا.
What do people do? People are indifferent at an 80-20 split.
ماذا يفعل الناس؟ الناس لا يبالون في انقسام 80-20.
At 80-20, it's a coin flip whether you accept that or not.
80-20، هو ربح ذو وجهين ما إذا كنت ستقبل أم لا.
Why is that? You know, because you're pissed off.
لماذا؟ لأنك منزعج.
You're mad. That's an unfair offer, and you know what an unfair offer is.
غاضب، لأنّ هذا العرض غير عادل.
This is the kind of game done by my lab and many around the world.
هذا هو نوع الألعاب التي نقوم بها في مختبري و في العديد من المخابر بجميع أنحاء العالم.
That just gives you an example of the kind of thing that
هذا يعطيكم فكرة بسيطة على ما تقوم به أنواع مماثلة
these games probe. The interesting thing is, these games
من الألعاب. الشيء المثير للاهتمام هو، أنّ هذه الألعاب
require that you have a lot of cognitive apparatus on line.
تتطلّب أن يكون لديك الكثير من الجهاز المعرفي على الخط.
You have to be able to come to the table with a proper model of another person.
عليك أن تكون قادراً على المجيء إلى طاولة المفاوضات مع نموذج مناسب لشخص آخر.
You have to be able to remember what you've done.
عليك أن تكون قادراً على تذكر ما قمت به.
You have to stand up in the moment to do that.
عليك للوقوف في تلك اللحظة للقيام بذلك.
Then you have to update your model based on the signals coming back,
ثم عليك تحديث النموذج الخاص بك استناداً إلى الإشارات القادمة إليك،
and you have to do something that is interesting,
و عليك القيام بشيء مثير للاهتمام،
which is you have to do a kind of depth of thought assay.
وهو فحص فكريّ عميق نوعا ما.
That is, you have to decide what that other person expects of you.
إذ أنّ عليك أن تخمّن ما الذي سيقرّره الشخص الآخر.
You have to send signals to manage your image in their mind.
عليك إرسال إشارات للتحكم بصورتك في عقل الآخر.
Like a job interview. You sit across the desk from somebody,
مثلا في مقابلة عمل. تجلس عبر المكتب قبالة شخص ما،
they have some prior image of you,
لديه مسبقا بعض الصور و الأفكار عنك،
you send signals across the desk to move their image
يمكنك إرسال إشارات عبر مكتب لنقل الصور
of you from one place to a place where you want it to be.
التي يمتلكونها عنكم من مكان إلى آخر حيث تريد لها أن تكون.
We're so good at this we don't really even notice it.
نحن نجيد القيام بهذا لكننا لا ندرك ذلك.
These kinds of probes exploit it. Okay?
بعض الوضعيات المشابهة تكشف عنها.
In doing this, what we've discovered is that humans
عند القيام بذلك، ما اكتشفناه هو أنّ البشر
are literal canaries in social exchanges.
يشبهون طيور الكناري في التفاعلات الاجتماعية.
Canaries used to be used as kind of biosensors in mines.
كان يتمّ استخدام طيور الكناري كنوع من أجهزة استشعار للعوامل البيولوجية في المناجم.
When methane built up, or carbon dioxide built up,
عندما تزداد كميّات الميثان أو ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
or oxygen was diminished, the birds would swoon
أو تتضاءل كمية الأكسجين، يغمى على الطيور
before people would -- so it acted as an early warning system:
قبل الناس - لذا فقد كانت كنظام للإنذار المبكر:
Hey, get out of the mine. Things aren't going so well.
مهلا، اخرج من المنجم. الأمور ليست على ما على ما يرام هنا.
People come to the table, and even these very blunt,
الناس يجلسون إلى الطاولة، وحتّى السيؤو الطباع منهم
staged social interactions, and they, and there's just
ينظمون تفاعلات اجتماعية، و هناك
numbers going back and forth between the people,
أرقام تتباين بين الأشخاص،
and they bring enormous sensitivities to it.
وهي تجلب حساسيات هائلة لهم.
So we realized we could exploit this, and in fact,
أدركنا أنّه بإمكاننا اسغلال هذا، وفي الحقيقة،
as we've done that, and we've done this now in
هذا ما فعلناه، و جرّبنا الأمر مع
many thousands of people, I think on the order of
العديد من الآلاف من الناس، أعتقد أنّ العدد يقارب
five or six thousand. We actually, to make this
خمسة أو ستة آلاف. ونحن في الواقع، نحتاج إلى عدد أكبر
a biological probe, need bigger numbers than that,
إن أردنا جعل الأمر دراسة بيولوجية،
remarkably so. But anyway,
لكن على أي حال،
patterns have emerged, and we've been able to take
ظهرت أنماط معيّنة، و تمكّنا من تحويل
those patterns, convert them into mathematical models,
تلك الأنماط إلى نماذج رياضية،
and use those mathematical models to gain new insights
واستخدام هذه النماذج الرياضية لاكتساب رؤى جديدة
into these exchanges. Okay, so what?
لهذه التّفاعلات. وماذا بعد؟
Well, the so what is, that's a really nice behavioral measure,
لقد كانت عملية قيس سلوكيّة جيدة،
the economic games bring to us notions of optimal play.
ألعاب الاقتصادية تكشف لنا عن مفاهيم اللعب الأمثل.
We can compute that during the game.
يمكن أن نحسب ذلك خلال اللعبة.
And we can use that to sort of carve up the behavior.
ويمكننا استخدام ذلك لتجزئة تفاصيل السلوك.
Here's the cool thing. Six or seven years ago,
الأمر الرائع بهذا الشأن، هو أنّه منذ ست أو سبع سنوات مضت،
we developed a team. It was at the time in Houston, Texas.
قمنا بتطوير فريق في هيوستن، تكساس.
It's now in Virginia and London. And we built software
وهو الآن في ولاية فرجينيا ولندن أيضا. وبنينا البرمجيات
that'll link functional magnetic resonance imaging devices
التي سوف تربط أجهزة التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي الوظيفي
up over the Internet. I guess we've done up to six machines
بشبكة الإنترنت. أعتقد أنّنا وصلنا قرابة الستة آلات حينها
at a time, but let's just focus on two.
ولكن دعونا نركز فقط على اثنين.
So it synchronizes machines anywhere in the world.
وهي تعمل على مزامنة الأجهزة في أي مكان في العالم.
We synchronize the machines, set them into these
نزامن الآلات، ثمّ نعدّلها للعمل أثناء
staged social interactions, and we eavesdrop on both
هذه التفاعلات الاجتماعية، ثمّ نراقب الدماغين
of the interacting brains. So for the first time,
المتفاعلين. في المرة الأولى،
we don't have to look at just averages over single individuals,
لم نحتاج مراقبة معدّل لعب أشخاص فرديّين،
or have individuals playing computers, or try to make
أو جعل أفراد يلعبون مع الحاسوب، أو محاولة صنع
inferences that way. We can study individual dyads.
تفاعلات من ذلك النوع. يمكن أن نقوم بدراسة ثنائيّات.
We can study the way that one person interacts with another person,
يمكن أن نقوم بدراسة الطريقة تفاعل الشخص مع شخص آخر،
turn the numbers up, and start to gain new insights
يصل بدوره الأرقام، وتبدأ في اكتساب رؤى جديدة
into the boundaries of normal cognition,
في حدود الإدراك العادي،
but more importantly, we can put people with
ولكن الأهم من ذلك، يمكننا أن نضع الناس مع
classically defined mental illnesses, or brain damage,
أمراض عقلية محددة بشكل كلاسيكي، أو تلف في الدماغ،
into these social interactions, and use these as probes of that.
في هذه التفاعلات الاجتماعية، وتستخدم هذه كتحقيقات من هذا.
So we've started this effort. We've made a few hits,
حتى لقد بدأنا هذا الجهد. لقد حققنا مرات قليلة،
a few, I think, embryonic discoveries.
قليلة، كما أعتقد، الاكتشافات الجنينية.
We think there's a future to this. But it's our way
ونحن نعتقد أن هناك مستقبلا لهذا. ولكن هو طريقنا
of going in and redefining, with a new lexicon,
للذهاب وإعادة تعريف، مع معجم جديد،
a mathematical one actually, as opposed to the standard
واحدة رياضية فعلا، بدلاً من المعيار
ways that we think about mental illness,
السبل التي يمكننا التفكير في المرض العقلي،
characterizing these diseases, by using the people
تميز هذه الأمراض، باستخدام الناس
as birds in the exchanges. That is, we exploit the fact
كالطيور في التبادلات. فعلينا استغلال حقيقة
that the healthy partner, playing somebody with major depression,
أن الشريك صحية، يلعب شخص ما مع الاكتئاب الكبرى،
or playing somebody with autism spectrum disorder,
أو يلعب شخص ما مع اضطراب طيف التوحد،
or playing somebody with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder,
أو يلعب شخص ما مع اضطراب نقص الانتباه فرط النشاط،
we use that as a kind of biosensor, and then we use
علينا استخدام ذلك كنوع منحساسات بيلوجية، ومن ثم نستخدم
computer programs to model that person, and it gives us
برامج الكمبيوتر نموذج ذلك الشخص، وأنه يعطينا
a kind of assay of this.
نوع من الفحص لهذا.
Early days, and we're just beginning, we're setting up sites
كنت مجرد بداية الأيام الأولى، وإننا، ونحن تقوم بإعداد المواقع
around the world. Here are a few of our collaborating sites.
في كل أنحاء العالم. وفيما يلي عدد قليل المواقع المتعاونة.
The hub, ironically enough,
لوحة الوصل، ومن المفارقات أن
is centered in little Roanoke, Virginia.
يتم توسيط في ليتل رونوك بولاية فيرجينيا.
There's another hub in London, now, and the rest
وهناك مركز آخر في لندن، الآن، وبقية
are getting set up. We hope to give the data away
يتم الحصول على إقامة. ونأمل أن يعطي البيانات بعيداً
at some stage. That's a complicated issue
في مرحلة من المراحل. وهذه مسألة معقدة
about making it available to the rest of the world.
حول جعلها متاحة لبقية العالم.
But we're also studying just a small part
ولكن نحن ندرس أيضا مجرد جزء صغير
of what makes us interesting as human beings, and so
لما يجعلنا مثيرة للاهتمام كبشر، وما إلى ذلك
I would invite other people who are interested in this
وأود أن أدعو الآخرين المهتمين بهذا
to ask us for the software, or even for guidance
أن يطلب منا للبرامج، أو حتى للتوجيه
on how to move forward with that.
حول كيفية المضي قدما في ذلك.
Let me leave you with one thought in closing.
اسمحوا لي أن اترك لكم فكر واحدة في الختام.
The interesting thing about studying cognition
الشيء المثير للاهتمام حول دراسة الإدراك
has been that we've been limited, in a way.
هو أننا كنا محدودين، بطريقة ما.
We just haven't had the tools to look at interacting brains
فقط لم يكن لدينا الأدوات اللازمة لإلقاء نظرة على العقول المتفاعلة
simultaneously.
في نفس الوقت.
The fact is, though, that even when we're alone,
والحقيقة، على الرغم من أنه حتى عندما نكون وحدها،
we're a profoundly social creature. We're not a solitary mind
نحن مخلوق اجتماعية تأثيراً عميقا. نحن لسنا عقل الانفرادي
built out of properties that kept it alive in the world
بني من الخصائص التي أبقت على قيد الحياة في العالم
independent of other people. In fact, our minds
مستقلة من أشخاص آخرين. في الواقع، لدينا عقول
depend on other people. They depend on other people,
تعتمد على أشخاص آخرين. وهم يعتمدون على أشخاص آخرين،
and they're expressed in other people,
وهم يعبروا في أشخاص آخرين،
so the notion of who you are, you often don't know
حتى مفهوم من أنت، أنت غالباً لا تعرف
who you are until you see yourself in interaction with people
من أنت حتى ترى نفسك في التفاعل مع الناس
that are close to you, people that are enemies of you,
القريبين لك، الناس الذين هم أعداء لك،
people that are agnostic to you.
الناس الذين هم أدري لك.
So this is the first sort of step into using that insight
لذلك هذا هي الخطوة الأولى إلى استخدام تلك البصيرة
into what makes us human beings, turning it into a tool,
إلى ما يجعل منا كائنات بشرية، تحول إلى أداة،
and trying to gain new insights into mental illness.
وفي محاولة لاكتساب نظرة ثاقبة جديدة من المرض العقلي.
Thanks for having me. (Applause)
أشكركم على استضافتي. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)